Guide to the Maurice Hindus papers M2002
Special Collections and University Archives, Colgate University Libraries
- Non-Hindus articles and speeches, 1926-1971
  - "Chamberlain is Defended by Lord Russell," Baltimore, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper, "Current History on Muzhik", 1929 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper, Max Frankel, "Dangers in Soviety Urge new Trend", 1960 March 20 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - "Evangelicals in the USSR", undated (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - Louis Fischer, "Did Stalin Want War?", 1941 July 5 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - V. Grigoryev, "Poetry of Discovery", undated (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - H.M. Kallen, "Religion in Russia," "The New Republic", 1927 November 2 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - Mark Lutz, Richmond, review of A Calendar of Sin by Evelynn Scott, 1931 December 14 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper article on Manchuria, 1927 December 18 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper article on Manchuria, 1927 December 1 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper article,Herald Tribune, "Maurice Hindus Day", 1931 December 7 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - Milton/Hindus (?) biography of Hindus, undated (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - TN, extracts from address of V.M. Molotov, 1940 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - Municipal Journal, "Moscow in the Making", 1937 April 9 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Newspaper, "Nazis Say Russia Will Aid on Food", undated (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - 4 articles on the strike in Passaic, NJ, 1926 March 17-31 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - Milos Safranek, "Czech Music, Literature, and Theatre Under the Protectorate", undated (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - The Evening Star, "Second of 14 Ex-Czech Officials Confesses Traitorous Plotting", 1932 November 21 (Box 26, Folder 32)
  - Upton Sinclair, "A Letter to Eugene Lyons", 1938 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  - New York Times, "Slansky Spy Trial Implicated West", 1952 November 22 (Box 26, Folder 34)
  - Smiglo's Speech in Cracow, no year August 6 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper, "Soviet Winter Urges End to Cold War in Literature", undated (Box 26, Folder 36)
  - Vilhjalmur Stefansson, "Farming Without Barns", undated (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - Arnold J. Toynbee, "America, England, and World Affairs", undated (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - Times, "USHA Takes a Leaf from Hindus' Book", 1940 March 5 (Box 26, Folder 39)
  - Carl Van Doren, "Prudence Militant", undated (Box 26, Folder 40)
  - Roger Williams,New York Times, "My Brother George", 1971 August 27 (Box 26, Folder 41)
  - The China Weekly Review, 1927 October-1928 January; 3 items (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Lyons articles and letters to the editor, 1937-1938 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    Also contains Hindus' rebuttals to Lyons' pieces.
  - Free Europe, 1940 March 22-August 9; 2 items (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - The New Statesman and Nation, 1940 August 3-10; 2 items (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Life, 1943 March 29; 1 item (Box 31, Folder 5)
    Special issue on the USSR.
  - The New Leader, 2 items (Box 30, Folder 3)
    Contains article "Marx and Alienation" by Sidney Hook. Also includes a tear sheet from the magazine Inside Nazi Germany with the article "The Story of March, 1848" by Professor Alfred Meusel.
  - Columbia Daily Spectator, 1968 April-May; 2 items (Box 31, Folder 6)
    Includes articles on student demonstrations and protests.
  - Harvard Today, 1969 Spring; 1 item (Box 30, Folder 4)
    Special issue on campus demonstrations.
  - Colgate Maroon, 1969 May 8; 1 item (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Konvitz, Milton R., "Why One Professor Changed his Vote,"New York Times Magazine, 1969 May 18 (Box 30, Folder 5)
- Contracts, copyrights, and royalty statements, 1926-1966
  - Contract for To Sing With Angels, 1941 June 27 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Contract for Hitler Cannot Conquer Russia, 1941 August 22 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Contract for To Sing with the Angels, 1941 September 30 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Contract for To Sing With the Angels, 1940 October 9 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Contract for the publication of Russia and Japan Must Fight, 1942 February 19 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Contract for To Sing with the Angels, 1942 March 9 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Contract for book about Russia, 1942 May 5 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Contract for new book, 1943 August 4 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Contract for Bright Passage, 1946 July 12 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Contract for Persian novel, 1947 February 5 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Contract for book on Palestine, Persia, Egypt, Iraq, and Iran, 1948 July 12 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Contract for In Search of a Future, 1949 July 5 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Contract for Magda, 1950 July 18 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Contract for Stalin's Major Blunders, 1952 January 3 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Contract for book on Russia, 1958 May 27 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Contract for book on Yugoslavia, 1961 June 7 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Contract for House Without a Roof, 1961 July 6 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - Contract for an untitled book on Russian politics (House Without a Roof), 1963 May 28 (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - Assignment of copyright Broken Earth, 1930 January 27 (Box 27, Folder 19)
  - Library of Congress, certificate of copyright registration,The Great Offensive,Broken Earth,Red Bread, 1933 August 10 and November 18, 1926 May 10, 1931 November 1 and May 7 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - Agreement of copyright, Russians tell M.H. Nazis won't reach the Volga, M.H. says Moscow appears festive and colorful, 1943 April 8 (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Copyright rights for Europe's Bright Spot, 1947 January 20 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Certificate of registration of a claim to renewal copyright Red Bread and Broken Earth, 1959 January 16
  - Copyright payment receipt for Red Bread and Broken Earth, 1959 January 16 (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - German rights for House Without a Roof, 1962 March 30 (Box 27, Folder 25)
  - Copyright rights for Green Worlds, 1962 May 7 (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Royalty statement from Victor Gullancz, Ltd., 1949 September 29 (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Royalty statement for Magda, 1953 March 10 (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Hammond, Hammond, and Co. Ltd. royalty statement, 1965 June 30 (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - A.M. Heath and Company, Ltd. royalty statement, 1965 December 14 (Box 27, Folder 30)
  - A.M. Heath and Company, Ltd., royalty statement, 1966 May 19 (Box 27, Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous tidbits, stock and bank correspondence, tax information, insurance information, bills, 1925-1971
  - Promotional posters, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Horsley Gantt's Guest Book, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Map of Germany and Poland, undated (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Assorted maps, Russia and Japan, undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Hindus, Letter to the editor,New York Times Book Review, 1941 October 26 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Hindus, "Tel Aviv: City of Optimism," The Star Weekly, 1948 April 17 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - TC,Herald Tribune, 1939 October 15 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - TLS, Treasury Dept. IRS, Boston, Massachusetts, Hindus; TL, Hindus, New York City, Mr. Geo W.B. Buitt, regarding audit, 1925 September 12, 1925 October 10 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Political map of central Europe, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Brochure for Harbin-South Manchuria Railway, undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Brochure for Manchuria, undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Russian newspaper cartoon, undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Russian newspaper, 1929 September 12 (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Russian newspapers, 1942; 3 items (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Visa-Russian, undated (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Russian Postcard, Jonkvera, "The Road to Yonkers", undated (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - Russian newspaper, undated (Box 28, Folder 16)
  - 2 PC-blank-Russian: "The First Woman Cosmonaut in the World," "A Woman of the USSR: Valentina Vladimirovna", undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
  - UN Security Council Ticket, Lake Success, New York, no year December 3 (Box 28, Folder 18)
  - Handwritten poetry-Russian, undated (Box 28, Folder 19)
  - Czech song about Czech songs, undated (Box 28, Folder 20)
  - Czech song, anti-Hitler, Czechoslovakia, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 21)
  - Wedding songs-Czechoslovakia, undated (Box 28, Folder 22)
  - Christmas songs-translated from Czech, undated (Box 28, Folder 23)
  - Czech songs-translated into German, undated (Box 28, Folder 24)
  - W. Sakharow, Librarian, PCS (C), Leningrad, USSR, Julio Kilenyi (Dr. Kuieslu), regarding Mark Twain, 1936 January 7 (Box 28, Folder 25)
  - "Les Soldats de Nationalite Hongroise a Leur Commandant Tcheque", 1938 November 12 (Box 28, Folder 26)
  - Telegram-Czech, V Praze, 1938 January 28 (Box 28, Folder 27)
  - ALS-Czech, S.W.I., 1938 June 14 (Box 28, Folder 28)
  - Telegram-German, Karlsbad, 1938 September 3 (Box 28, Folder 29)
  - Numbered verse-Czech, undated (Box 28, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Czech Documents, 1938 (Box 28, Folder 31)
  - 2 TLS-Iran?, undated (Box 28, Folder 32)
  - Iranian Embassy, 2 ALS-Iran, Washington, D.C.?, Tehran, undated (Box 28, Folder 33)
  - Mirror, review of Siege, New York, 1940 March 31 (Box 28, Folder 34)
  - News, review of Siege, North Carolina;World, review of Siege, Oklahoma;New York Times, review of Siege, New York, 1940 March 31, 1940 March 24, 1940 March 17 (Box 28, Folder 35)
  - Maps of Russia-Russian, undated and 1928; 2 items (Box 28, Folder 36)
  - Founder's certificate-Willkie Memorial Building of Freedom House, Maurice Hindus, undated (Box 28, Folder 37)
  - Invitations and meeting in memory of Samuel Harper, no year March 5 (Box 28, Folder 38)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, New York, New York, regarding trustee appointment, 1931 June 30 (Box 28, Folder 39)
  - American Trends of Czechoslovakia, regarding reception invitation, 1941(?) September 26 (Box 28, Folder 40)
  - Money-Brazil, undated (Box 28, Folder 41)
  - PCS, F. Munk, Czech, 1938? (Box 28, Folder 41)
  - Autographed photo of Robert S. Alter, 1929 February 20-21 (Box 28, Folder 42)
  - Business card-Professor Albert Pinkevitch, undated (Box 28, Folder 43)
  - Business card-Mr. John Dewey, 1929 June 19 (Box 28, Folder 44)
  - Obituary from Colgate paper, undated (Box 28, Folder 45)
  - Certificate of Literacy, 1940 October 15 (Box 28, Folder 46)
  - Hindus, "Misquoted,"Boston Post, 1938 March 26 (Box 28, Folder 47)
  - TN, 1948 February 29 (Box 28, Folder 48)
  - TC, newspaper articles, 1941 October 7, 21, 28 (Box 28, Folder 49)
  - Bestatigung-Vienna, 1963 August 6 (Box 28, Folder 50)
  - Colgate University library catalogue-Russia and Japan, undated (Box 28, Folder 51)
  - Exchange ration card, undated (Box 28, Folder 52)
  - Transcontinental and Western Air, Inc. exchange order, undated (Box 28, Folder 53)
  - Dress ad, undated (Box 28, Folder 54)
  - Post card from France, undated (Box 28, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous unmarked envelopes, newspaper bits, etc., undated (Box 28, Folder 56)
  - TLS, Harry Kraus, Cleveland, Ohio, Hindus, regarding stick, 1928 March 14 (Box 28, Folder 57)
  - TLS, Standard Trust Bank, Ohio, Hindus, regarding claim, 1935 January 9 (Box 28, Folder 58)
  - TL, Hindus to Chase National Bank, Dallas, Texas, regarding letter request, 1939 March 7 (Box 28, Folder 59)
  - Bill of sale, Harvard Hall Corp. stock, 1945 August 7 (Box 28, Folder 60)
  - American Casualty Company stock schedule, 1963 June 6 (Box 28, Folder 61)
  - A.L. Stamm and Co. stock statements, 1964 February 3 (Box 28, Folder 62)
  - Chase Manhattan Bank statements, 1966 January 6 (Box 28, Folder 63)
  - New York State tax information, 1965 (Box 28, Folder 64)
  - IRS payment stub, 1965 September 15 (Box 28, Folder 65)
  - New York state tax information, 1968 (Box 28, Folder 66)
  - TL, Hindus to Charles L. Behn, Dallas, Texas, regarding life insurance, 1939 March 7 (Box 28, Folder 67)
  - Rochester American Insurance Company, 1954 September 11 (Box 28, Folder 68)
  - TL, Hindus to Continental Casualty Company, regarding coverage, 1966 April 30 (Box 28, Folder 69)
  - U.S. Fidelity and Guaranty Company, 1966 August 23 (Box 28, Folder 70)
  - Hotel Ambassador, Praha, Bill for Mr. William Shirer, 1938 November 22 (Box 28, Folder 71)
  - Hotel receipt, Assouan, Egypt, Hindus, 1945 December 1 (Box 28, Folder 72)
  - Bill for Hotel Astoria, 1960 August 2 (Box 28, Folder 73)
  - Bill for Moscow Belgrade, 1961 August 9 (Box 28, Folder 74)
  - Bill for Hotel Kummerwein, 1961 September 15 (Box 28, Folder 75)
  - Bill for Palace Hotel, Stockholm, 1963 June 11-12 (Box 28, Folder 76)
  - Bills and Checks for Victoria Apartments Corporation, 1951 October 1, 29, 1951 November 1 (Box 28, Folder 77)
  - Bill for Avista Painting and Contracting Co., 1965 January 14 (Box 28, Folder 78)
  - TL, Hindus to United Medical Service, regarding bills, 1967 January 5 (Box 28, Folder 79)
  - TLS, Gordon Harvey to Hindus, New York, New York, regarding refund-Medicare, 1968 June 17 (Box 28, Folder 80)
  - Medicare bill for Frances, 1971 August 17 (Box 28, Folder 81)
- Photographs, undated
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Hindus, promotional poster, undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Hindus and Colgate Administration, undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Pictures taken from York Hill, undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Photos of Jim Moore's house, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Photo for Red Bread promotion, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Small photos of Hindus, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Hindus, writing, undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Hindus, portraits, undated (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Hindus, The High School Student, undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Hindus, "Pencil Portrait", undated (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Hindus,The Contemplative Writer, undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - North Brookfield, undated (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Hindus' Class Reunion Picture?, undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - Classroom Building, Colgate, undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - Photograph, Jim Moore, undated (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - Lower Campus and Taylor Lake, Colgate, undated (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Dorms at Colgate, undated (Box 29, Folder 18)
  - Hindus, The Lecturer, undated (Box 29, Folder 19)
  - Photograph, The Chautauqua Speakers, undated (Box 29, Folder 20)
  - Hindus, On the Air, undated (Box 29, Folder 21)
  - Hindus at Colgate, undated (Box 29, Folder 22)
  - Passport, undated (Box 29, Folder 23)
  - Two framed portraits, Hindus, undated (Box 29, Folder 24)
  - Photograph, Russian, undated (Box 29, Folder 25)
- News clippings, 1933-1968
  - Great Offensive, 1933 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Soviet German pact, undated (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Late Czechoslovakia clippings, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Czech clippings, 1939 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1938-1939 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - German reviews, "Die Enkel der Revolution", 1968 (Box 30, Folder 11)